Pengyu Cheng

☑ pengyucheng95@gmail.com • ⑤ linear95.github.io

Introduction

I am currently a senior researcher at Tencent AI Lab, primely working on dialogue systems and controllable text generation. I also have a broad interest in machine learning methods to improve the controllability, interpretability, and fairness of deep models.

Education

Duke University08/2017 - 05/2021Ph.D., Electrical and Computer EngineeringAdviser: Lawrence CarinTsinghua University08/2013 - 07/2017B.S., Mathematics and StatisticsAdviser: Jiwen Lu

Experiences

Tencent AI Lab 08/2022 – Present

Senior Researcher Supervisor: Zhengyou Zhang

Dialogue systems, controllable text generation, and interpretable language understanding.

Tencent Interactive Entertainment Group (IEG)

06/2021 - Present

Senior Researcher

NLP applications (dialogue systems, controllable text generation) in gaming scenarios.

Information Initiative at Duke (iiD)

08/2017 - 03/2021

Research Assistant Adviser: Lawrence Carin

Probabilistic and information-theoretic learning methods , and applications in natural language processing.

Microsoft Cloud and AI

06/2020 - 08/2020

Research Internship Mentor: Jingjing Liu

Improving self-supervised multi-view contrastive learning with learnable data augmentations.

NEC Laboratories America

05/2019 - 08/2019

Research Internship Mentor: Martin Renqiang Min

Improving disentangled text representation learning with information-theoretic guidance.

Selected Projects

Dialogue System for Virtual Characters in Games

08/2021 - Present

Role: Project Leader

Built from scratch a dialogue system for virtual characters in gaming scenarios.

- implemented the intent detector based on JointBERT to jointly detect intents and fill slots; designed a data collection pipeline for fine-tuning detector with game-related intents and slots.
- o designed a **objective-oriented knowledge** module for virtual characters to remember and update knowledge with respect to particular games.
- o constructed a multi-style template-based generator to response with different sentiments and characteristics.

Text Style Transfer for Virtual Characters Speaking

10/2021 - Present

Role: Project Leader

Constructed a web application for transferring virtual characters speaking content with target style attributes.

- o designed a style transfer models based on **synonym** words replacement *w.r.t* word usage frequencies of styles.
- o filtered transferred text samples by the **perplexity** score calculated by the target style language models.
- o Supported style transfer tasks in virtual character dialogue and game intelligent commentary.

Controllable User Nickname Generation

06/2021 - 12/2021

Role: Project Leader

Constructed a controllable nickname generation pipeline with pretrained language models.

- o implemented vanilla nickname generation model by finetuning GPT-2 on user nickname data.
- o discovered **stylized** nickname generation, by pre-training GPT-2 with stylized text then finetuning model on nickname data; generated nicknames in poem, lyric, and Kung-fu styles.
- o designed keyword-based nickname generation via masked language models with GPT-2, T5 and BART.

Selected Publications

- o **P. Cheng***, W. Hao*, S. Yuan, S. Si, L. Carin, "FairFil: Contrastive Neural Debiasing Method for Pretrained Text Encoders", In *ICLR*, 2021
- S. Yuan*, P. Cheng*, R. Zhang, W. Hao, Z. Gan, and L. Carin, "Improving Zero-Shot Voice Style Transfer via Disentangled Representation Learning", In ICLR, 2021
- o **P. Cheng**, W. Hao, S. Dai, J. Liu, Z. Gan, and L. Carin, "CLUB: A Contrastive Log-ratio Upper Bound of Mutual Information", In *ICML*, 2020
- o **P. Cheng**, M. Min, D. Shen, C. Malon, Y. Zhang, Y. Li and L. Carin, "Improving Disentangled Text Representation Learning with Information-Theoretic Guidance", In *ACL*, 2020
- o **P. Cheng**, Y. Li, X. Zhang, L. Chen, D. Carlson, L. Carin, "Dynamic Embedding on Textual Networks via a Gaussian Process", In *AAAI*, 2020 Oral
- o **P. Cheng***, D. Shen*, D. Sundararaman, X. Zhang, Q. Yang, M. Tang, A. Celikyilmaz, and L. Carin, "Learning Compressed Sentence Representations for On-Device Text Processing", In *ACL*, 2019 Oral
- o **P. Cheng**, C. Liu, C. Li, D. Shen, H. Ricardo, and L. Carin, "Straight-Through Estimator as Projected Wasserstein Gradient Flow", In *NeurIPS* Workshop, 2018 Spotlight

Services & Awards

o Reviewer/Program Committee for ICML, NeurIPS, ICLR, AAAI, IJCAI, ACL, EMNLP, N	AACL, ARR.
o Fellowship of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Duke	08/2017
o First in Duke-Tsinghua Machine Learning Summer School (1/112)	08/2017
o Academic Excellence Award of Tsinghua University (top 30%)	10/2014
o Top 5 in the 18-th "Sogou Cup" Artificial Intelligence Programming Contest (5/200)	04/2014
o Silver medal in the 28-th Chinese Mathematical Olympiad (CMO)	01/2013
o First Prize in Chinese National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces (NOIP)	11/2012

Technical Strengths

Computer Languages: Python (Tensorflow, Pytorch), R, C/C++, Java

Software & Tools: LaTeX, Emacs, Mathematica, MATLAB, Excel, Markdown